so I thought we could discuss the
importance of
Faith practice
why um for example
it's the first of the five faculties
faculties of the noble disciple that the
Buddha described the first one is Faith
and um in many occasions it's said
that yonar which the Buddha said is the
condition for the arising of the right
view it depends on faith as
well so and so and
uh
because you know there's there's a
certain uh sort of tendency especially when
uh sort of tendency especially when
Buddhism came to the west where it's
thought of as like a it's not really
something you have to accept it's more
like something
that uh you take it or leave it
depending on whether it resonates with
your experience like only the parts that
resonate with you and that seem true to
you uh you accept and then the rest you
can not not considered part of Buddhism
if you want you can you can pick and
choose from within the Buddhist teaching
basically yeah so um definitely there
would be some benefit to that so to
whichever extent the person adopts it it
would be beneficial but it's a different
question now to say whether it's
possible to to attain the Right View
based on such an
attitude so we can start
so we can start
by contemplating reflecting on how what
a lack of faith
obstruct uh not all practice but let's
say sufficient
practice how does lack of faith
obstruct the
practice which would otherwise result in
stream entry and or more accurately
before we even go into that what is
Faith because yeah we some people hear
that word and might confuse it with the
faith of faith in God or something like
that Faith Christianity but there are
some overlaps but um they shouldn't be
thought of as exactly the same thing so
we could clarify that first like what is
Faith this is something that I thought
was interesting there I think in a few
sutas it talks
about kind of discussions among
householders in the Buddhist
time and specifically when they would
speak about other householders who were
basically that they kind of held in low
esteem one of the things that they would
often say is like so and so is faithless
he he does not have
faith and to me that was interesting
because that kind of it wasn't faith in
something specific it almost seemed like
it was pointing to a specific type of
attitude that could be brought towards
different things so could you
I guess could a person who
is
seeking some kind
of basically somebody who's beginning a
noble search have faith even if it's not
could they have the um the attitude of
Faith even if there's not yet something
that they're kind of putting it into I
guess is
the question
and my thought is it would kind of have
to be that attitude of like admitting
you don't know
and being open to the fact that somebody
may know which already presupposes that you
know which already presupposes that you
have acknowledged that there is a
problem right right um if you don't
recognize that the house is on fire then
you wouldn't make any move to get out
and you wouldn't uh feel that there is a
need you would see any value in somebody
who knows how to put out the fire
because you think that house isn't on
fire yeah so it begins by having some
recognition that there is suffering
which is actually in that same suit it
says that Yar depends on faith but what
does this Faith depend upon I think it's
another one but it does it does say
there's definitely the statement says
suffering is what gives rise to Faith
yes this is was trying this is what I
was trying to get at so somebody needs
to have
recognized um that having been born is
is is not one big part but actually
fairly problematic to to begin with so
they need to be honest about that and
then the faith Rises like you know even
the Buddha who did not find in the end a
teacher that showed him fully the way
out but even he had that Faith Like an
escape from all this must be possible
because otherwise this is just a doomed
situation which he did not accept that
is in essence it seems to me but faith
is like it's not worthwhile going on
with any of this so so that there has to
be a way out that is the basic attitude
it seems to me of Faith at least how it
starts then then once you have discern
to way out then the quality of that
Faith changes uh in the sutas right the
the faith of the noble one is not in its
nature the same as as when you start but
but we can discuss those distinctions
later on yeah yeah so it's um that that
the component of faith is what enables
you to
push beyond what you your current
situation put it that way because uh
actually it's it's even part of that
mundane quote mundane Right View that
the Su talk about that says there is
mother there is Father there's given
there's a result of action uh and at the
end it says there are athetics and
brahmans who have understood understood
this world and next so then that's
already one something that uh
you know for many might be hard to
accept like that there that that it
isn't just a kind of subjective um sort
of everybody has their own
interpretation and and it's kind of uh
nothing it doesn't really matter in the
end whereas no it says mundane Right
View is is uh at least being open to the
possibility that some people have
actually rightly understood that there
is such a thing as right understanding
yeah um so
that's uh that's what would first of all
open open you up to the possibility as
well that
that
uh your present understanding is the
reason why you suffer that's why then
faith comes before wisdom even because
uh even for the five faculties of noble
disciple because that Faith keeps that
kind of um keeps you questioning
yourself because you see that there's
something ahead of you kind kind of
thing like and even the Buddha said when
when he um I think shortly after his
Awakening he said well I I don't have
any teacher I haven't uh learned this
from anyone um but uh you shouldn't live
without respecting
something and then he said well I will
then respect the dhama and uh that's
another thing that's that's quite
connected with faith that sense of
respect but it shouldn't be confused
with uh which is what I was sort of
getting into before shouldn't be
confused with uh piety which is kind of
the more usual conception of Faith which
is like a often kind of what you see in
Buddhist countries like like it's kind
of just a blind uh performance of
certain observances and and and but when
it comes to like well am I seeing this
as valuable in the context of of you
know changing my behaviors and my
actions uh in in daily life that aspect
is is something that's more hard to find
that somebody somebody has that attitude
so that is more of a like you could put
it that way uh actual Faith needs to
have an effect on your actions if it if
it doesn't if it just a belief well yeah
that's what it would be it would just be
a belief but um that's not what faith
really is Faith should be connected with
a sense of something that needs to be
done MH not just a empty conviction that
you proclaim the Buddha is the best but
you don't live to uh align yourself with
those values
so yeah so to get the
motivation that there is
uh Al without experimenting it uh by
oneself in the moment but there is a a
way which is uh which has been
uh experimented and also fulfilled by by
other Sage wise people and so this thing in
Sage wise people and so this thing in
the the motivation
is to keep in mind exactly yes because
uh there has to be that quality of
um basically
realizing how deep uh wrong view goes
It's kind of um often times people don't
have that recognition they think oh
sometimes like I I am ignorant or
something like that so sometimes I fall
off the practice but uh it's it's a much
more broad where without faith you won't
be going to the root that's why it says
without faith you cannot have y you will
not go to the source of your ignorance
like because there's always layers and
layers and layers of assumptions of
questioning things that you don't
question things that you take for
granted uh tendencies that are just
purely based on on uh craving on getting
pleasure and avoiding pain so even when
you know things that might seem uh
justified in the context of dhama like
you know uh I don't know helping
people in the monastery or something and
then you kind of if you if you don't have
you kind of if you if you don't have
enough faith and you see well clearly
the Buddha said um being engaged with
distractions and he even spoke about
that like a monk who spends um his time
uh distracted he's not progressing the
practice but then if you don't have
enough Faith it's not necessarily that
you would think like oh that's wrong or
something but you wouldn't kind of snap
out of it with enough strength to see
wait I am actually falling into this and
and that's a very coarse example but
it's it's to the to the like to the
whole range of all the factors of the
noble Aid full path in order to acquire
those factors you need to be willing to
accept wait but my view might be wrong
my intention might be wrong my um speech
might be wrong at any given time if you
have faith in the Buddha in the
practical sense you would be willing to
accept that U maybe you sure you're better than
that U maybe you sure you're better than
before but there are still more and uh
that that's really that that purpose of
faith and it's um and another thing that
that's I think people often Overlook is
that you know there's often the
descriptions of stream entry as sure
understanding um the for noble truths
and and all those things but uh you know
many people can say that they understand
things so that that's kind of a very um
in the end it's not necessarily a very
reliable criteria but uh what they also
say more acutely than than understanding
in the sutas as the factors of stre mry
is that unshakable Faith or absolute
faith in the Buddha dhama yeah which uh
isn't sometimes see that that that's a
kind of a a fine line to to thread there
because it says there that the they also
are independent of a teacher so see it's
not the same type of faith of like you
know uh you know hugging just constantly
hugging the legs of the teacher and and
and just going wherever they tell you to
go and and not having a mind of your own
yeah there's not blind obedience exactly
it's uh but at the same time it is
unshakable Faith to the point where you
know it's also said that that that's
what what would allow a
community of people to live together in
harmony which is the right view in that
sense like and and you have that that other s
like and and you have that that other s
where these three monks were
staying together and they say um
sometimes they would have an idea about
something and then they would say oh but
why shouldn't I do what these other
venerables want to do and so that's kind
of um but see you cannot get that by
like okay now let me just not have
preferences let me just pretend that
that I that I go along with what
everybody else does because that's a
byproduct of the right understanding so
it's more like a like an indication
let's say that that you have understood
things properly but it's not about
fabricating a sense of of just blind
obedience to to to seniors or blind
obedience to to wherever you take as a
teacher it it should be more like okay
but I think I understand okay but do I
now do I have that that unshakable
confidence and and Faith whereby
basically I'm ready to at any time um
revise my understanding yeah can we say
that faith is that quality or faculty
that prevents you from stagnating but
keep digging deeper until there is no
doubt so that is right because uh in in
other Traditions there might be an
attitude like somebody suffers from
doubt and then you say don't doubt
believe right and then the belief
becomes the sort of the opposite of the
doubt but what we are saying here it
seems to me is no no cultivate doubt
because you have faith that there is
more to be understood exactly which is
quite a different take on what faith is
yeah yeah it's uh Faith would have to
Faith is what would allow you to admit
that you're still subject to doubt
because uh that like you said it's it's what
uh that like you said it's it's what
will make you push far enough will make
you dig deep enough until you find that
which cannot be doubted yeah and then
you have but if you have automatically
when you don't have faith in something
you have faith in yourself that that's
not that doesn't take like a conscious
effort or or faith in your views let's
say faith faith in whatever you happen
to be your in your current kind of
situation uh and in in order to make
progress you need to have faith in
something other than yourself like
that's at least in the context of dhama
um well even actually in mundane terms
like if somebody's taking a treatment
from a doctor and they have more faith
in what they think is the right thing to
do about that illness and then the
doctor tells them well you're supposed
to wake up at 2: a.m. and take this pill
don't take it at any other time of the
day only at 2: a.m. but if they think
they know better they will take it
whenever whenever it's more convenient
or not take it at all and because of
that they won't get cured so it's a it's
not necessarily an a kind of conscious
choice that I choose to be faithless
it's just by not um let's say uh
considering that direction or the
importance of that direction and most
importantly by not seeing the
predicament that you find yourself in
like if the person also
uh doesn't feel that the sickness that
they have is such a big
deal yeah they might you know have sure
they have they they believe that this
doctor know knows what he's talking
about but if they they don't really feel
that sense of urgency to cure themselves
then then that that also will lead to
the lack of faith in the proper sense as
I just said faith that leads to that
affects your actions not just your
beliefs your actions and your beliefs
plus the Cure is not necessarily
Pleasant so in order well yeah waking up
at 2 a.m. is not yeah so in in in order
to sustain the right practice which is
not necessarily Pleasant there needs to
be the faith which is going to bridge
that Gap because that faith is saying no
no that this pleasure that you now
suffer from that can eventually
disappear um if you stick to this so
there is a there is somewhat of a
relation particularly in the beginning
between faith and time like the only
pleasure you know is sensual pleasure
that's painful you don't know anything
else but there is the faith that it is
still worth well to restrain those
sensual Pleasures because to be free
from that is more peaceful even though
that peace you presently do not have
yeah yeah and and and of course again it
it cannot be like I just decide to have
this belief that is possible to be free
from sensal pleasure you need to have
seen the problem yeah of your current
situation that's the only way that the
faith has that proper footing as we said
that depends on suffering recognizing
suffering there's also that suta that
says what's the result of suffering it
says either uh Madness or vexation yeah
or Noble search and that Noble search is
basically exactly that it says actually
the scripture says who knows uh a way or
two to to be free from the suffering
that's right yes so so um that's exactly
then when the Bas then the faith gains a
basis where you recognize the the con
conundrum that you're in
and there was even when suta I I came
across recently that said that um there
are things that are unpleasant to do uh
but have a pleasant unpleasant to do but
have a pleasant unpleasant result um
Pleasant to do that have a pleasant
result unpleasant to do that have a
pleasant result and pleasant to do that
have an unpleasant result
and then it says how do you um tell
apart the the wise from the
fool and it says it's because you know
even when you tell the fool don't do the
thing that's Pleasant to do but leads to
unpleasant results he will still do it
when you tell him uh to do the thing
that's unpleasant to do but least to
Pleasant results he won't do it and then
the opposite for the for the wise person
in other words the fool is concerned
with immediate pleasure only because he
doesn't have faith because he doesn't
the he doesn't recognize the the yeah
like I've been saying the the that he
needs to get out of this the situation
that he finds himself in and and that's
that's really where the Dharma applies
like the Dharma isn't supposed to be
like a public teaching for everyone in
the world um I mean sure if people can
everywh keep the five precepts but that
not that's not specifically uh uh what
the dhma is the dhma is for people who
recognize an issue with their current
way of being so yeah with that existence
basically in the world yeah yeah so uh
that is where Faith begins and so um the
suas as well they find that there's a
there's various formulations of these
five faculties but uh uh one of them
also includes the the sense of fear uh
sorry sense of Shame and fear of
wrongdoing mhm which also depend on
faith because see
um often times you know there are things
that seem pretty
harmless uh that that people might not
think are a big deal like you know some
people don't think killing mosquito is a
big deal or or drinking alcohol from
time to time is a big deal but that
sense of Shame and and fear of
wrongdoing which is in regard to un
wholesome states which is one of the the
powers of a noble disciple
like that depends on faith in the sense
that no it doesn't matter how that that
I right now think that this doesn't seem
a big seem seem like a big deal because
I know that I'm still subject to
ignorance so um in other words I P the D
first I know that okay if if the Buddha
said this and I am claiming to be aiming
for the same goal that the Buddha taught
then I cannot honestly at the same time
say like I am applying the
treatment but at the same time I think I
know better yeah exactly yeah yeah so uh
yeah which comes then back to what we
said at the very beginning this attitude
of picking and choosing what you like
from the discourses that's going to be a
problem to the degree that one has been
developing Faith because the dhama is is
it's One Vision it's one teaching so
this attitude of picking and choosing is
only possible when there is some lack of
faith and then also of course the
tendency will be to reject the things
that you should have the most sense of
urgency to accept because that that's
where the wrong views are going to be
most uh strongly established because
there is a natural tendency to not want
to be disturbed and uh to be let's say
peaceful whereas whereas actually if you
want to OT the issue then then that is
bad that definition going going to be
disturbing so so so well like I said
unpleasant now but yeah so against the
grain also depends on faith like why
would you go against the grain if you
don't have faith that in the long one is
worthwhile that's a that's the phrase
like as said the dhama goes against your
grain or against the stream
so only if you know that there's
something better at the top of the
stream you have faith otherwise
everything else is is going to be convincing you no
else is is going to be convincing you no
actually I should just just keep going
because why why would I just try to swim
against see everybody else is just going
down there why am I the only one who's
who's swimming back up yeah so yeah but
that's a that's a very inauthentic way
of regarding things because you are
already giving more authority to the
group or to what everybody else is doing
but if the Buddha was thinking like that
he would never have be G the Buddha yeah
of course but the thing is these
pressures and these uh Tendencies of
your mind uh
they they might still be there but again
faith is what allows you to go against
it whereas if you don't have the faith
as a grounding you just go with whatever
and even even the wisdom as well um like
uh it's common to to have a especially
with westerners to have a very kind of
intellectual analytical uh approach but if then it's
analytical uh approach but if then it's
not that that's bad necessarily but then
if the faith gets sort of pushed away
and not seen as important then uh
ignorance fundamentally is like infects the whole
fundamentally is like infects the whole
of your experience and so those the
concepts and and ideas that you that you
might be operating with yes you need to
improve them and and upgrade them but if
that's all you rely
on um fundamentally ignorance will still
be uh sort of running the show whereas
faith is kind of that outside
um sort of input the utterance of
another kind of that outside input that
okay yes I have to understand it for
myself it's not just about agreeing with
all the what this person says but I put
the teaching first at least while I'm
trying to to develop it I put the
teaching first and then my reasoning
second and um uh what I was going to say
is is that's actually one of the better
ways to right regardless of what teacher
you follow uh it would actually be much
more of an authentic and sincere way of
going about it to have that that um
recognition of well if if I if I have
any chance of actually uh you know
getting the right View and abandoning
ignorance I have to commit myself like I
I can't be picking and choosing MH uh
because that's um like imagine just a
doctor who who says oh well
um you got to take these
pills and uh there might be other pills
that will have you know what's it called
similar effects no no like they will
sort of nullify the effects of these
ones that you're taking oh so then the
person goes to the other Doctor Who
prescribes them exactly those pills and
then you know they're taking both at the
same time and how will they
know that which of the two doctors was
actually like they they have no way to
know whether both of them were
wrong or whether one of them was wrong
both of them so it's so it's better to
commit to one teaching fully even if it
then turns out to be a wrong teaching at
some point at least you can then say
with certainty this didn't work and and
that's what the Buddha did actually and
then your Noble search continues but if
you have like several teachers and you
don't see contradictions between those
teachings or you do but you kind of just
but then you pick and choose in in in
order to make it somewhat coherent
according to your own standards then you
can pursue that for the rest of your
life but if it doesn't bring any results
you will not be in a position to Now
find out what was actually beneficial
and and what wasn't exactly yeah that's
that's not the very popular approach
these days uh most of the time a sort of
open-mindedness is what people you know
seem to prefer rather than to just stick
to one thing but actually that is
probably a shortcoming as we now
discussing yeah and and it's not a then
about because you do have that suta
where the Buddha says
um how how do you preserve the truth or
how do you guard the truth and it says
until you've seen it for yourself you
shouldn't be talking as if you know this
is certain this I know this for sure but
at the same time you do have a a sense
of well right now this is what I am
applying myself to uh so then everything
else for now because I developed enough
faith I investigated as as says you
visit the teacher ask questions
investigate Ponder
reflect then Faith arises then you have
a sense of of okay this is actually
worthwh committing to and at least for
that duration if you have a in order to
have a real chance of of um whe being
able to judge for yourself whether that
teaching was truly right or wrong you
need to actually apply it in in that
sort of um focused sense and uh that's
what the Buddha did with his with his uh
former teachers like he he he um they
taught them they taught him these
formless attainments and stuff and uh
you know while he was in the training
period let's say he was committed to
that practice and only then when he
wasn't like oh no I'll disagree with
this part and because of that he
actually got to experience exactly what
the teachers were telling him to do to
the point that those teachers asked him
to become a teacher as well and then he
said but wait this is not good enough
exactly so you would have that that
sense of because you tried it you would
see okay it's not because I did what I
wanted I didn't listen to the doctor I
did exactly what he said and yet I'm
still not cured now at least you can
take that box okay this doctor is not
the right but if you were following 10
doctors at once like we said before yeah
you're not you're not any closer yeah so
so so that's confusing and also one
slightly ironic thing with this attitude
of picking and choosing is
like when you see like when you you when
you abandon that attitude for example
and you stay with the sutas and you
discover how internally consistent
actually a great many discourses are
across the board that's precisely a
factor which increases Faith yeah but
you but but you would never get that if
you if you don't question that attitude
of of of picking and choosing and and
actually the Buddha said in one
discourse that at at least is at his
time he asked Ananda do you see even two
monks in this assembly who have a
different interpretation of the teaching
and he said no so the fact that you feel
like you need
to uh mix and and pick and
choose um yeah you don't want to come to
two quick conclusions about who's right
and who's wrong but you cannot
authentically and sincerely allow
yourself to think that all of these
people are in line with what the bu was
teaching either if if they're teaching
contradictory uh things on that
fundamental level as the budha said in
regard to this discourse I just
mentioned it was about do you see any
two monks who teach a different
interpretation of the four catanas of
the noble Aid full path of the four
right drivings of the five faculties and
you would see even amidst you know
teachers in the same tradition you often
have such very Stark differences but
people kind of uh wave it away hand wave
it away but saying oh no it's just uh
this is for people with certain tendency
and this for people with another
tendency but that's not what the teacher
is saying though so you are kind of uh
he's saying everyone should be doing
this yeah and so you you you're kind of
allowing yourself to bend it into into
what you think that's how quickly it
goes and and you don't realize as well
that um fundamentally you cannot like
Escape your your perspective you can't
just have like a perfectly objective
point of view where you're judging
everything your standard for judging is
your own view which is what causes you
suffering it's what what's infected with
with ignorance and so um
like if you don't question it you're not
really growing in that sense you kind of
cuz another person why why does this
other person who also claims to be
following the buddh teaching why is his
mix so different from mine and then I
cannot honestly claim that we're both
heading in the same direction but it's
this kind of um
yeah inauthentic or or shallow U uh
shallow shallow effort of reflection
often because again it's not regarded as
important a lot of the times like
clarifying these sort of broader aspects
is not that important it's just just do
the practice just do the meditation and
then all these things just will
magically sort
of piece together and yeah that's also
Faith but about naive one perhaps well
it's yeah because it's it's it's not the
faith that um that's leading you to
question yourself I just said it's it's
kind of Twisted it's like even then you
would have like a certain ideal of what
you think nibana is and and and you're
kind of picking and choosing which
practice will take me to that instead of
saying wait do I actually know what the
goal is and that's that type of faith
that would push you back to that far far
um background level where you're going
to be questioning everything from the
ground up yeah because when you just
start you don't actually know what the
goal is exactly yeah or or or you might
say because that's a for Noble choice
you don't see the sensation of suffering
then yeah so you might say well the goal
is to be free from suffering but that
doesn't necessarily mean that you've
understood the full extent of suffering
yeah in fact another disciple will have
because that's Al revealed with the
formable truth yeah and and
so that's what um how you get to see
that that
uh well well without that faith for
example oh there's more to this than
many things that are actually just
management of feelings like feeling
better calmer because you're
managing uh you wouldn't have if you
don't have faith you you wouldn't have
the incisiveness to actually question
and see actually I'm still liable to
suffering so yeah it's a it's a it's something
so yeah it's a it's a it's something
that
not necessarily uh you develop it kind
of
like um directly but you can certainly
recognize in yourself a lack of faith
and then uh as the budha said the the
conditions for Faith well reflect on um
do you actually feel a sense of urgency
do you actually feel as as the Buddha
said that that um you know for someone
who hasn't realized the for no truths
it's like they
he said uh because what should somebody
do if their head is on fire he said they
should apply unwavering effort
diligence uh
recollection uh perseverance in order to
extinguish that fire yeah and he said
well somebody might actually let the
fire be not pay attention to it and it
would actually be more important to make
an effort to discern the for of truths
so it's always kind of a
um hyper bow in the sense but it's it
goes against a common kind of understanding
against a common kind of understanding
that oh we just have to be satisfied
with with where you are right now like
you know uh all these attainments and
stuff these are just uh more forms of
becoming and so it's more important to
just just accept yourself as you are now
and then just just be with that and
that's how you just deal with it yeah
yeah but the Buddha is saying
you should see your situation as if your
head is on fire mhm yeah so that's CLE a
problem
yeah yeah I wanted to maybe like briefly
go back to like this kind of tendency of
trying to find justification like with
the teaching or was anything else but in
this context with the teaching and I
wanted to ask like someone can like
listen to this discussion and say okay
from now I will stop
make justification for myself but that's
kind of changing the things to like kind
of an opinion level but not yet to the
view so I wanted to ask
like I think it would be kind of
relevant to kind
of make the distinction between like
what an opinion A belief is and what a
point of view is because it's quite a
different thing you mean uh justify like
in terms of actions yeah yeah yeah
well yeah it's when
um the thing
is always then if you have that attitude
of oh it's just it's just this I just
correct this am I already in the right
path so whichever shape that takes if
you don't assume like okay I'm not
justifying myself anymore but do you
stop there do you keep looking like Okay
but well do I know the extent of action
for example like sure I'm restraining my
my uh obvious uh bodily verbal mental
actions but uh am I sure that there
isn't more to this principle of
wholesome and un wholesome that I'm not
yet considering so then yeah you accept
like you have like an opinion of um yeah
I shouldn't act out of this and uh
that's something that you can acquire in
just a moment you just read a book it
says okay don't do this and that's it
but changing your view uh takes much
longer takes training takes takes
um upgrading your criteria for what even
like the terms that you're using to
begin with like wholesome and wholesome
craving abandoning uh mind
abandoning uh mind
Consciousness are those like do you feel
like that's it or do you recognize
actually even those things I cannot be
sure I understand so then when I'm
saying I am purifying my mind from UNH
wholesome states that might not mean for
me what it should mean for example uh
and um yeah that's how you you see that
there is that extra
Dimension between you just accepting an
opinion from something you read or or
some something somebody told you and
then developing or or adjusting your
view according to it there's that extra
dimension of like how okay you agree
with what they said but how are you
actually interpreting it
internally uh so five Aggregates you
know that's a that's a common example
like yeah people talk about the five
Aggregates but they never sto to
question the fact that maybe their
definition of what five constitutes is
either inaccurate or too vague or or not
just overall not really referring to
what the Buddha pointed to with the with
these things so that's what faith would
would um allow you to to consider at
least that um there's that constant
Improvement that needs to be made
constant questioning even for a noble
disciple it's not a matter of just okay
now I just mechanically do um this
practice the Buddha said even
um you cannot become an anagami so would
not be able to become anagami if they
lack faith
so it's um obviously they have
unshakable faith but it can always be
increased and uh deepened further
so but like I said it's it's uh not
something you increase directly it's the
clarification so um first that sense of
urgency am I covering up the sense of
urgency as well through distractions and
sensuality which makes me feel like
everything is all right finding safety
in in the world um that's one way then
also developing Clarity so that's when
then it's not just about faith you also
have to um clarify for example read the
sutas and and clarify the teaching so
that it doesn't feel anymore like this
vague ambiguous kind of yes I have to
give a craving but I I don't really know
what that means you you make it more
sort of
concrete and then you get a sense of
what you need to do and that increases
your faith in that sense because you see
oh wait it's not even like um this
mystical because you mystify things and
you make them kind of put them too far
away from you then that's also not Faith
anymore it needs to be uh Faith yes it's
over there but I also have a recognition
of what I can do at least to bring me
closer to that direction so um CL the
Buddha called that measuring the task
like measure what it is that you
actually need to do and then on account
of that the the
the faith or you would say the the
desire or the the Zeal to do it arises
yeah that's a good point because
sometimes faith can be an excuse to do
something like I just have faith which
are practically not doing anything but
what we're talking about is the faith is
precisely what enables you to go there
yeah exactly right yeah it's not just oh
this I have and then theight in that
Faith or right which is sometimes like
devotion which but there can be an
attitude of of inity just making excuse
like yeah I have devotion but
practically you're not really doing
anything yeah devotion can result from
Faith but not the other way around
necessarily no so because you would
still see you know in in the in the
sutas like how the MS would be even when
they were Arun they would say like they
somebody would come and ask them a
question and uh they would say well you
shouldn't ask me I'm not the one who
knows it's the teacher he's the Buddha
is the one who knows and uh even though
they were AR so you could see that yes
there was a sense of devotion there but
if you just fabricate
that really makes yeah yeah but perhaps
it it can also be helpful to clarify if
it right in order to like find a
starting point like faith in the sutas
even with the Buddha it is like seeing a
dead person just in the streets somebody
who is old or sick that is what for the
Buddha kindled that search that that
that Faith so suffering is not like oh I
I I have particular problems like uh my
child's misbehaving or my or my marriage
is going down the drain these are all
particular things sure that's all un
unpleasant but actually that faith is on
the level as we said earlier of f
existence like even if if everything is
now going according to your wishes
you're still subject to old age sickness
death and that is by the by the hair is
on fire so that faith in its nature
covers the whole of your life it's not
this particular situation or this
particular problem that is now occupying
your mind um it's much it's much bigger
picture yeah yeah that's why we said
it's it would have to have an effect on
the way you live your life if it's if
it's genuine Faith yeah it cannot just
remain as a as an empty conviction yeah
so so people can ask is the fact that
I'm subjected to old age sickness death
genuinely a problem for me or not so
somebody thinks well this is the only
life I just try to live to to sit out to
right as comfortably as possible and
then that's it that's going to be an
obstruction to Faith as well and you
would be surprised how many Buddhist
kind of have that view like it's it's oh
well you know it's it's um I'll just do
the best in this life and then
um whether they believe in rebirth or
not they might say oh well I just get
reborn in the next one and and do my
best and uh then I'll do the work yeah
yeah like right now I have family I have
children I cannot do it right now I'll
do it later and um yeah that means sure
you still recognize the value in a
ambiguous sense of Enlightenment but I
like to compare that to like somebody
who let's say they already earn um
100,000 per year and then they have the
option to gain 1 million and so sure I
would like to do that but if it takes
too much of my effort and too much my of
my energy I might just rest U com
comfortable with what I already have uh
and then that's kind of the the
interpretation that that a lot of people
have behind like stream entry and and
all these things but uh it's not
something that you're gaining it's a
it's a huge problem that you need to
lose it's your head being on fire
and if you see it in that way that's not
something that you can be just kick your
legs up and okay I'll just just stay
with my head on fire um so it's um it's
uh if it doesn't feel like that
uh kind
of like basically there isn't anything
else really that's worth it apart from
this then you you haven't recognized
sufficiently the perilous situation that
Samar is yeah so with the with the
proper Faith you cannot say I'm doing
this practice but there's also something
of equal importance next to it exactly
that that that that cannot that cannot
be yeah